so what exactly is inertia
how would you describe it
inertia is the tendency of an object to
resist changes in its state of motion
now if you recall newton's first law
states that an object in motion will
continue in motion and an object at rest
will remain at rest unless acted on by
net force
so if you have an object
it's going to remain at rest unless you
try to push it
and
that's just the tendency of natural
things
things tend to remain in the state of
motion that they're in
so an object at rest wants to continue
at rest and an object that's moving it
wants to keep moving unless it's acted
on by a net force to accelerate it or
friction to slow it down
so inertia
is a property of an object
that resists any changes to its state of
motion
so if an object is at rest
inertia wants to keep it at rest
now to illustrate the property of
inertia
we're going to use two objects
the first object has a mass of 10
kilograms
and the second object
has a mass
of 100 kilograms
so in both cases we're going to apply a
force
of 50 newtons
so which object do you think has more
inertia
the object with less mass or more mass
intuitively you know it's the object
with more mass
it's easier to move a lighter object but
it's more difficult to move a heavier
object because the heavier object
has more inertia
so inertia is proportional to mass
now based on newton's second law
net force is the product of mass and
acceleration
so the acceleration
is going to be the net force
divided by the mass
so for the first object
it's a force of 50 divided by a mass of
which will yield an acceleration of 5
meters per second squared
for the second mass it's 50 divided by
which will give us an acceleration
of 0.5 meters per second squared
so as you can see the small object has a
very large acceleration
the large object has a small
acceleration
so what this tells us is that
the lighter object
has less inertia
because it was so easy to accelerate the
object
with a small amount of force
the larger object has more inertia
because even though we apply the same
amount of force
the acceleration of the object
is a lot smaller
so whenever you increase the mass of an
object
the inertia of that object will increase
so inertia
is proportional to mass
it's harder to change the motion
of a heavy object compared to a light
object so an object with a lot of mass
it's very difficult to get it to move
so
that's the basic concept between inertia
as it relates to translational motion
now what about rotational motion how
does inertia play a role in that
so let's compare two objects
the first one
is the thin hoop
and the second one is a solid disc
so for the thin hoop
the mass
is concentrated
at the edge of the circle
and for the solid disc the mass is
distributed throughout the circle
now let's say that the mass
of the thin hoop
is 10 kilograms
and the mass of the solid disc is the
same
so they both have the same mass
and let's say that the radius
of both objects is the same
we'll say the radius is 2 meters
so which one has more inertia
is it the thin hoop
or is it
the solid disk
what would you say
so if we took a string
and attach it to each object
and we apply the tension force
that's the same
let me draw this picture
make sure that the angle is the same
so let's say if we apply the same
tension force
of 100 newtons
which one
will be easier to rotate
is it the thin hoop
or the solid disc
and keep in mind the radius is the same
for both objects
so which one has more inertia or is
inertia the same
now you might be thinking that the
inertia is the same because it has the
same mass
and the radius is the same however
the inertia is not the same
because the distribution of mass is
different
it turns out that the thin hoop has more
inertia
than the disc
with all else being equal
the equation for the inertia of the thin
hoop
is mr squared
it depends on the mass
and also on the radius
the inertia of the disc
is the mass times r squared but
multiplied by a half
so this factor
one half
is based on the distribution of mass
throughout the disc
the fact that this is one is due to the
fact that the mass
is concentrated away from the center
so whenever the mass
is away from the central axis of
rotation
the inertia increase
so if you can move the mass away from
the axis of rotation you can increase
the inertia of the thin hoop or whatever
object you're dealing with
if the mass
is closer to the axis of rotation
then the inertia
will decrease
so the inertia
of an object that can rotate depends not
only on the mass of the object
but also
on how that mass is distributed
relative to the central axis of rotation
so looking at the thin hoop
all of the mass
is concentrated away from the axis of
rotation and that's why it has
a higher inertia value
with the disc some of it is at the edge
some of it is
in the middle some of it is close to the
axis of rotation
here you have no mass at the axis
rotation but here you have some and so
that's why the inertia of the disc is
not zero it's not one but it's in
between it's one half
so if you can put all the mass away from
the axis of rotation you can increase
the inertia if you put it closer towards
the axis of rotation then the inertia
decreases
so the thin hoop
has more inertia which means it has more
resistance
to rotation so it's going to be harder
to rotate the thin hoop
the solid disc however because it has
less inertia it has less resistance to
rotation
so it's easier
to spin a solid disc but it's harder to
spin the thin hoop
so where does this equation come from
mr squared where do we get that quantity
so this is the inertia of a thin hoop
and the inertia for a solid disc is one
half
m r squared
and the inertia for a sphere
is two fifths
m r squared
so we can see that this constant
in front of the term mr squared has to
do with the way the mass is distributed
among the object and also the shape of
the object as well
so sometimes i tend to refer to that
quantity as c c for a constant
now let's talk about how we can derive
m r squared for the inertia of an object
so let's start with newton's second law
f is equal to m a
now let's multiply both sides
by the radius r
so on the left side f times r
is equal to the torque
the rotational equivalent of force
just as force is a push or pull action
that can cause an object to accelerate
forward or decelerate
torque
can cause an object to
rotate it can speed up while rotating or
slowing down while rotating
so let's think of torque as the
rotational equivalent of a force
now the acceleration
is equal to the angular acceleration
times the radius so let's replace a with
alpha times r
so the torque
is equal to m r squared
times alpha
so therefore the sum
of all the torques in the system
is the sum of all
of the mr square quantities times alpha
and just as force
is equal to mass times acceleration
torque
is equal to inertia times alpha
so torque is the rotational equivalent
of force
alpha
is the rotational equivalent of a a is
the linear acceleration
alpha is the angular acceleration
now m the mass
provides
inertia to an object as you increase the
mass
the resistance
of the object increases in the sense
that it's harder
to move a heavy object than a lighter
object
so this is the inertia of an object
with reference to
translational motion
this quantity
is rotational inertia
is the resistance of an object
it's the object's resistance to
rotational motion
so therefore we could say that inertia
is the sum
of mr squared
and so that's how you can relate inertia
to this equation
using this process
so this equation that we have here
it's associated with newton's second law
for rotational motion
whereas this is newton's second law for
translational motion or linear motion
you